Guide to the New American Movement Records TAM.051
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
New American Movement Records
circa 1971-1982
TAM.051
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
19.5 linear feet in 20 boxes
The New American Movement (NAM) was established in 1972 by veterans of the New Left who wanted to move beyond the activism of the 1960s and rejected a Communist "vanguard party" approach to organizing. NAM's overarching goal was to create a democratic socialist society, characterized by racial, sexual and economic equality. In 1982, the organization joined with the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee to form the Democratic Socialists of America. This unprocessed collection contains conference and convention materials, correspondence, minutes, position papers, reports, educctional materials, commission, task force and chapter files, issues of NAM's discussion and internal bulletins, printed ephemera, some files on other socialist and left organizations, of which some contain discussion NAM's relations with these organizations, including discussion within NAM on whether or not to merge with the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee to form the Democratic Socialists of America.
New American Movement (Organization).
Box 1-20
Historical/Biographical Note
The New American Movement (NAM), a self-identified "new type" of socialist organization, held its founding convention in Minneapolis, Minnesota in 1972. Established largely by veterans of the New Left, NAM wanted to move beyond the activism of the 1960s and rejected a Communist "vanguard party" approach to organizing. The group was opposed to the Vietnam War and called for the impeachment of President Richard M. Nixon. NAM's overarching goal was to create a democratic socialist society, characterized by racial, sexual and economic equality. In 1982, the organization joined with the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee, led by Michael Harrington, to form the Democratic Socialists of America.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Materials found in collection; provenance is unknown. Accession numbers associated with this collection are 1980.009 and 2011.016. Additionally, a copy of a police report on the New American Movement was donated by Joel Blau in 1998; its associated accession number is 2014.077.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Democratic Socialists of America Records (TAM 105)
Michael Harrington Papers (TAM 209)
Scope and Content Note
This unprocessed collection contains conference and convention materials, correspondence, minutes, position papers, reports, educctional materials, commission, task force and chapter files, issues of NAM's discussion and internal bulletins, printed ephemera, some files on other socialist and left organizations, of which some contain discussion NAM's relations with these organizations, including discussion within NAM on whether or not to merge with the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee to form the Democratic Socialists of America.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (U.S.).; Democratic Socialists of America.; New American Movement (Organization).; Bulletins.; Correspondence.; Minutes.; New Left |z United States.; Printed ephemera.; Reports.; Socialism and youth |z United States.; Socialist feminism.; Socialist parties |z United States.; Student movements |z United States.
- Chicago Conference, Oct 1, 1971 (Box 1)
- Thanksgiving Conference, Nov 1, 1971 (Box 1)
- Founding Convention, Jun 22, 1972-Jun 25, 1972 (Box 1)
- Second Convention, Jul 5, 1973-Jul 9, 1973 (Box 1)
- National Council (Box 1)
- National Interim Committee (Box 1)
- National Office Correspondence (Box 1)
- Economic Task Force (Box 1)
- Baltimore, MD Chapter (Box 1)
- Chicago, IL Chapter (Box 1)
- Middlesex, MA Chapter (Box 1)
- Minneapolis, MN Chapter (Box 1)
- New York City Area Chapter (Box 1)
- Peoria, IL Chapter (Box 1)
- Pittsburgh, PA Chapter (Box 1)
- Iowa City, IA Chapter (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1971- (Box 1)
- Middle East Discussion (Box 1)
- Membership Lists 1971- (Box 1)
- Position Papers 1971- (Box 1)
- Interim Internal Bulletin, circa 1971 (Box 1)
- New American Movement and People’s Party Merger (Box 1)
- New American Movement and International Socialists (Box 1)
- National Interim Political Committee of People Working for a Mass Political Party (Box 1)
- Socialist-Feminist Conference, 1975 (Box 1)
- Sojourner Truth Organization (Box 1)
- Wisconsin Alliance (Box 1)
- Notes (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence (Box 2)
- Correspondence & Conventions (Box 3)
- Conventions & Movement Organizations (Box 4)
- Training Schools, Correspondence, Miscellaneous, New American Movement Commissions (Box 5)
- New American Movement Commissions, New American Movement Organizing, Office Files (Box 6)
- Office Files, National Council (Box 7)
- National Council (Box 8)
- Branches, Davenport Conference (Founding Convention) (Box 9)
- Miscellaneous Office Files (Box 10)
- Office Files & Movement Organizations (Box 11)
- Movement Organizations & New American Movement Chapters (Box 12)
- New American Movement Chapters (Box 13)
- New American Movement Chapters (Box 14)
- New American Movement Chapters (Box 15)
- New American Movement Commissions, National Files, New American Movement National Council (Box 16)
- Miscellaneous Subject Files, Miscellaneous Materials, Printed Ephemera (Box 17)
- Printed Ephemera (Box 18)
- New American Movement Discussion Bulletins and Printed Ephemera (Box 19)
- Publications, printed ephemera, internal documents, and some correspondence of Marvin Gettleman, donor of this box of materials [bulk 1970s] (Box 20)